Yay, welcome back to Lamrim.
And
we're just waking up here in Arizona, so
don't don't
take it too seriously.
We were just finishing up something from
yesterday
and then we're going to move to a new
topic. It's the last sentence from
yesterday.
You guys see it? It says Dorna. Dorna.
m d o r n a
Okay, Dorna send day kun ni long te ge
wa kon che kyang.
Any good deed you do with the motivation
of
bodhicitta. Did you find it? You guys?
Yay.
Kon che kyang. Good. De pen ni sem chen
tam che kyi don da number jung sum. So
to wrap up from yesterday,
if you have this feeling in your heart
that what's your ultimate goal in life
is to help countless beings
and you can just try to imagine it.
And again for me,
I like to pretend I'm in a spaceship.
I take off from this world.
I just head out
in any direction
and I keep going and there's no end to
it, right? There's no there's no
skin to the bubble that you hit the edge
of the universe and you have to stop or
something like that. There's nothing.
You keep going.
And if you do
small things in your life like making
coffee
from motor oil. I'm
just kidding.
Then
I'm really just kidding. It's quite
good.
If you just make a coffee or something,
but it's with that motivation,
then
what Pabongka Rinpoche is saying here
is that you can multiply
that good deed
by the number of beings that your
spaceship is passing.
Okay, so billions of home goons, okay.
And it's so
efficient. And by the way, I think it's
probably
the only way you can become a Buddha
because a Buddha
requires so much karma. So, you I guess
you would have to make karma with
countless beings to create it to become
a Buddha.
So, let's do it. All right. We finished
five benefits so far. And the
esteemed friends in the room
who are all veteran Dharma practitioners
are going to tell me the five first of
the first of the 10 benefits.
You join the family.
You join the team. What did you say?
The family. Join the team.
Yeah, you join the family. Good. Yeah.
It's like joining a mafia family.
And uh
you become part of the family. What's
the picture?
Tennis player.
Tennis player. Okay. Second one?
You get a name.
Yeah.
Yeah, you graduate. You get a degree.
You are now a bodhisattva.
Okay. Third one? Oh, what was the
picture? Yeah, graduation picture.
Third one?
It's a little bit difficult. It's the
sun and the birds.
That's the camel.
Oh, you outshine.
Yeah, you outshine. Yeah. The sun is
more glorious than uh
than the beautiful graceful birds. The
beautiful graceful birds are cool, but
the sun is a little bigger.
Okay. Um
number four?
What's the
What's the picture?
Not two
Yeah, coffee shop.
So, we become a buy object of beautiful
coffee.
Yeah, I think that was super sexy. I
mean just to think that uh
It's a weird It's a weird angle, right?
Like we don't think that way very often.
But if we became a really good person
then all the person around us could make
more good karma.
Uh
if they just make us cough and stuff
like that.
So wouldn't that be nice to be that
good? Okay, that's a kind of an unusual
twist.
Uh
number five and that was I'll give you
the picture.
It's the men on the beam on the sky
scraper.
No, you keep wanting to do the men on
the beam.
Or what is it? How about the big
equipment?
Yeah, the big equipment. The men on the
beam are way back uh
Oh.
like the Buddha
paradises are going to shake because I
forgot
I even forget what part that's in. Oh.
Yeah, it's like joining the family. They
They're throne shakes and then they say,
"Hey, we got a new kid in our family."
Something.
Okay, uh So Kyabje Rinpoche said it's
over. Yeah.
Super efficient way to collect more good
karma. Not picking up rocks one by one
anymore.
Uh
it was
We should go out and do it just for fun.
Uh
just to give people the feeling of what
it's like.
Okay, so we're on number six, okay?
Benefit number six.
And uh
And but uh I was going to show the
planets, but I let's forget it.
Uh
which is
if you get to bodhicitta
it's extremely powerful
for
wiping out old bad seeds, okay?
Bodhicitta is extremely powerful
as an antidote
for wiping out old bad karmic seeds,
okay?
Just uh
dream
of helping uh infinite numbers of living
creatures
is enough to cancel a lot of our old bad
deeds. And you know, those of us who've
been practicing our whole life,
uh we still do bad deeds. We still make
mistakes.
Uh we still yell at people and stuff
like that.
We still say bad things about coughing
and stuff and hurt people's feelings and
and uh
we still make mistakes all day. So,
wouldn't it be nice if there was some
kind of
powerful way to just
cancel all those stupid little mistakes
we make all day. And and so, that
intention
or that feeling is what we're going to
cover next, benefit number six.
The picture is
a
the sun, the surface of the sun.
Here we go.
Okay.
It should be item 30. Yeah. Okay. So, I
I want you to imagine
that uh you're eating french fries
in the car
and trying to drive at the same time,
which never happens.
And it's really hard to get the ketchup
right when you're driving.
Uh you know, it's also dangerous. Uh I
suppose you're also on your cell phone
at the same time.
But
but uh
you know,
you've had this experience where you put
on a nice shirt or a nice blouse and
and you're going to someone's wedding.
This happened to us recently. And then
you spill ketchup on the
on the blouse and you're like, "Yeah,
yeah, yeah, shit." And uh it's too late
to turn out and go back home and you're
trying to drive and clean it at the same
time and
imagine to clean that ketchup stain
on your shirt, you send it to the middle
of the sun.
Okay, the laundromat
of the middle of the sun. Sun I'm trying
to Why did Geshe la pick that picture?
I think I was going to a wedding and
spilled ketchup on my shirt.
And then I was trying to think of some
extremely powerful way of removing a
stain.
You know, and and and I looked it up and
I forgot what it was. Uh but the the
temperature at the middle of the sun
I don't I don't know. So many 50 million
degrees or something.
And
and that's the chance that your bad
seeds have to survive bodhicitta.
Okay, that's the chance that your bad
seeds have to survive bodhicitta. If
your bad seeds come close to bodhicitta,
it's like ketchup stain in the middle of
the sun. Okay? And
and I think it when we originally taught
this we it was during the heavy virus
times and we were talking about removing
that seed
uh with bodhicitta. Okay?
So here we go. Chupa ne Digpa Dawa la
ong dele lapa mente.
Even for me forget collecting good deeds
good seeds,
but for cleaning away bad seeds,
there's nothing better than bodhicitta.
Bodhicitta's number one.
Lapa mente chinjugle. Chinjug says,
"What's chinjug?" For $3.
Chang chub sem bed chupa lang chupa
Yeah, guide to the bodhisattva's way of
life. It says and he keeps using this
text, right?
Digpa tobcha shintu mi sempa tenyi tobpe
chang chub sem minpa yeshe kang ki silki
number yer. They'll silki number for
$20.
I'll chain. Yay! $3.
$20 for Janice.
Uh but silki number here means
uh, the the body cheetah.
Sucking numbers the ketchup thing.
See the big difference, right?
Uh, okay. The body cheetah
outshines, it overwhelms the
the little bad deeds we did all day
long, okay? Or the big ones also, okay?
So, he's
who is it? Who's talking?
Master Shantideva is comparing body
cheetah
to something which outshines completely
your bad They don't stand a chance
against your body cheetah, okay?
Uh,
even the worst bad deeds, he says here,
All right. Shapita shapashankin the big
kitchen to chill one.
There may be things we've done in our
life
which were so serious
that even if we use the four powers,
it's difficult to remove them, okay? Uh,
it's difficult to
freeze them, freeze dry them,
okay? Uh, d k p s a p a g u d
But if you're able to just
think about
helping countless beings,
s a p a g u those bad seeds will be
finished off, s a p a finished.
Papa told me key.
Then he talks about Arya Sangha, okay?
Papa told me
key lochani sushupti big u a l a
He practiced in the cave, as you know,
and here's his picture
with the dog.
Item number 31.
Uh,
yeah.
Uh, he practiced for 12 years in a cave,
as we know the story, right? Because
we've been studying the
lion's dance,
uh,
which is, you know,
which he taught after learning it from
Maitreya.
Uh after he was able to see Maitreya by
taking care of a dog, okay, taking care
of a wounded dog.
Okay, good. Say about Papamaki,
Lochiniki, Dupagewale, he practiced in
the cave
for 12 years. But Nying-je len-chi true
compassion for a single minute was more
powerful for him.
Okay, he spent 12 years in the cave
doing Maitreya's
mantra and asking Maitreya to come.
And then a few minutes with the with the
the hurt dog on the highway
uh ended up being more powerful for him.
So, he's comparing that moment of
compassion for the dog to
a moment of Bodhicitta
could clean away your bad deeds faster
than doing the four powers over and over
again, okay.
By the way, those those items have
numbers, you guys. Number 31, I'm on
number 31.
Uh
37 31. Okay, I maybe I forgot to say
anything. Uh Nying-je len-chi ke but dip
dip jo wa le che sha pa chu.
Che sha pa means much more powerful,
okay.
Okay, Shang Nyam Digpa Shintu here's
another quotation.
And he likes quotations. There we go.
There's the Sangha.
Oh, yes, Sangha. Oh, you had him?
This is not mine.
Oh, sorry, okay. Digpa Shintu me se chin
na yang, pa la te ne di pa cham bo ta.
Ka la te ne yu ke du ge wa. De la ba cha
nam ki chi mi ten.
Digpa Shintu me se chin na yang, even if
you make big mistakes in your life, and
we all did make big mistakes in our
life.
But
If you're in a very dangerous situation,
but you have a friend
who is extremely powerful.
It's It's like you can just turn to them
and say, "Help Help me out."
I remember I was in college.
And my One of my friends said, "Hey, you
want to go to mountain climbing?" You
know? And I'm like, "Yeah, sure."
You know? And he was a
a very expert mountain Big big guy
and an expert mountain climber. And And
so, I said, "Yeah, I'll go."
And uh so, we went and And then, he
climbed up a cliff.
A very high
cliff.
And I was down at the bottom, and I'm
like like this.
And he went to the He got up at the top.
He climbed over a negative incline.
And got up over the cliff. And then,
he's like, "Hey, Mike, come on. Let's
try it."
And I'm like,
You know? I said, "No. I don't want to."
Then, there was a His girlfriend was
with us.
And she's this small lady with
with blonde hair, you know? Kind of like
Katie.
And she says, "Oh, I'll do it."
And she climbs up with no rope.
Negative cliff, you know? Gets up to the
top. I'm sorry. I can't do that.
Then, I thought, "Well, I can do that."
You know? And he said, "Well, you better
rope I better rope you." You know?
And so, So, I climb up.
And he's holding the rope around his
waist somehow, right? And uh
I fell.
And I fell at the
at the negative part. And And he
He was holding me with one hand.
You know? And he was like, "Ha ha ha."
And I'm like,
Anyway, it's
the image here.
Okay, you're in a dangerous mountain
pass.
And then you you're you're in great
danger.
And then there's one big powerful guy
who knows what the heck he's doing and
he saves you, okay?
Who's that?
Bodichita, okay?
Karma Tenzin Yuthok Tulku
If you ask them for help, they help you.
Yuthok means
in a moment, you know, in the moment of
trouble they hold the rope.
And then you don't fall.
If you are any kind of a
wise person who knows how to
take care of themselves,
then why wouldn't you ask them to hold
the rope?
If you and if you're not a fool,
you say, "Oh, please hang on to that
rope, okay?
Uh hang on to Bodichita, okay?"
Uh and then uh Palbokam said, "Explain
I'm going to I'm talking too fast,
right, Tenzin?"
That always happens in the morning.
Uh
I slow down later.
Shay Sum Metar Sam Day Yuna
If you have Bodichita,
Dig Dip Don Day Debu
Uh
you can escape the
Chung Jig Bay Chung, okay? Chung Drol.
This is an interesting expression, Chung
Drol,
because it's the title of the Tibetan
Book of the Dead.
Okay, so the real title of the Tibetan
Book of the Dead is
uh
saving yourself from the
Okay, there's a I met a guy who climbed
Mount Everest.
And uh
I I I didn't know about it, but there's
a
When you get to the top, the last five
yards, the last five meters
is a ridge of ice.
To get to the real top, you have to
balance. The last thing you have to do
at the top of the world is to balance on
a ridge, and it's like 6 in wide.
And it's 30 It's 30 ft or something.
It's like 10
you know, 10 m balancing with a full
100-lb pack and on oxygen.
And that's the only way to get to the
top. And then
you know, that's called tongue duel. The
real title of the Tibetan Book of the
Dead is uh
trying to cross the last
the last knife edge.
It's called the knife edge in the in the
top of the mountain. It's the real name.
Uh knife edge meaning the bardo, okay?
By the way, that text is
is famous for being mistaken. So, I
don't suggest it, and I don't
I don't think you should study it. And I
know people have been hurt by studying
it.
Uh who who So, but it's a The name is
very cool.
Which is the knife's edge at the top of
the world, okay?
Uh so, in this case, you need someone
who's, you know, got the rope, who who
brings you up. And that's what he's
doing.
And that's what Pabongka Rinpoche says
Master Shantideva is talking about.
Who was the first person up the mou-
Hillary. It's called Hillary's Crest.
Well, he would He doesn't count cuz he
was
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Anyway, it's called Hillary's Crest or
something.
All right. Jim Jim Nyima Tsering
Dorje Chang Dorje Drolma
Tsering Drolma. If you have a big
guy helping you up, you don't feel so
scared, okay?
All right.
I think we have a picture there
somewhere.
Yeah, there we go.
Who's the guy in the blue jacket?
Bodhicitta, yeah, good.
And then you don't have to be so scared
about
big mistakes you made in your life.
That's the cliff.
That's the mountain cliff, okay, cool.
And the Bodhicitta will take you up past
that.
Teny Duta Meshi Dichen Nam
Do say Duta
Te
Me
So this is the Te Te is the Ta in
Tarchin.
What's that mean? Tarchin?
Yeah, the end, okay. Du means like Dune
core.
Kalachakra
Du
Kala
Time, yeah. So this is called the fire
of the end of time.
The fire at the end of time.
And this is uh like a nuclear fire that
destroys this planet, okay?
And and
it's actually when the sun goes
supernova. So Buddhism
Abhidharma Kosha third chapter
third chapter describes uh at the end of
this sun
it will supernova and it will consume
the earth
in a it will envelop the earth in flame.
And then some texts say it'll be a a
war, some kind of
incredible weapon which burns the entire
earth. So
anyway
Bodhicitta is similar to that flame.
Like in the way that the sun can
supernova and melt this it will
According to Abhidharma
it will vaporize this earth. And so you
got to get the idea that your Bodhicitta
can vaporize
your bad deeds. Okay, if you get a
little Bodhicitta
you can vaporize
big bad deeds you did in the past.
They will just turn into
air and disappear, okay?
Yay.
No matter how big is your poopa of bad
deeds.
Okay, don't forget that poopa can mean
heap of of leaves from a tree.
But it can also mean uh
a huge mountain, okay?
All right. If even if you have a
mountain of mistakes you've made in your
life,
if you took a piece of dry wood
and set it in the middle of the sun,
okay?
It would be disappear. Those bad seeds
would just disappear, okay?
Therefore,
if what you want to accomplish
is simply to remove your own bad seeds,
you can spend a hundred years doing the
four powers, but
it would be better for you to spend one
meditation session on bodhicitta.
Okay. Let's say it again. You could do
four steps for a hundred years
or he says
and he doesn't say better, he says quite
supreme, infinitely better to spend an
hour on trying to think about
bodhicitta, okay?
Yay.
I don't know about you, but me, I don't
know.
In that hour, I will also collect some
new bad seeds.
I don't know. Anyway,
it's like
it's like a sand castle.
All right.
Okay, so we're on to benefit number
seven. All right.
What was the picture from benefit number
six now? What picture we going to use
for our meditation later?
Those were in the in the presentation,
but what was the main picture?
About the Dutaime.
Yeah, the sun
putting a ketchup stain
in the middle of the sun, okay.
All right. Now, here's
another picture. This is from Shenzhen.
These are all the buildings in Shenzhen.
Uh
and
I don't know. Shenzhen's one of my
favorite places in the world.
Uh
it's kind of what New York used to be in
1970s or something.
And it's extremely vibrant and
beautiful.
The city didn't exist until 1970s or
something.
And now it's 25 million people.
And it's all new, and it's all
incredibly beautiful.
And they they have done a lot to make
sure the city is beautiful. So, every
for every skyscraper there's a park.
And it's amazing. It's really beautiful.
And
and it's the center of
of innovation for the world really right
now. So, anyway,
uh
all of your wishes come true. Benefit
number seven, okay? If you
if you develop bodhicitta, then all of
the wishes
in your heart come true, okay?
Let's go see what the text says.
Uh dimbini samde kepa na nekup don
tartak den tamche pemedu.
If you're able
to spend some time
every day
thinking about helping
not just people in your country
or people in your family or not just
people The big thing I think is we have
to move beyond
imagining helping all the people in this
world
cuz that's not many.
Okay? It's only a hundred billion or
something.
All the living creatures, okay? So
it's a lot more important. Uh it you got
to break through
from this planet to other planets. It's
it's foolish
to think that if life can occur on one
planet
and if the planets are infinite
then there's not infinite planets where
there's life. It's just foolish to think
that way.
Uh
We haven't met other planets' people
yet.
But maybe they don't want to meet us.
I don't know. You know, I mean there's a
pretty easy explanation.
You know.
I mean
I mean you know, somebody in your office
is I don't know why nobody ever asked me
out to lunch.
And you're like, well
it's kind of hard to explain.
Maybe you should brush your teeth once
in a while. Okay, anyway.
Uh
So you got to break out
from the limitations of this beautiful
blue planet. And you you got to put your
mind further, okay? It's it's pretty
simple.
It's easy to break out from one town to
another town.
It's easy to imagine helping helping
people from another country.
But but if you're going to play this
game
you got to break out from this planet,
okay? You got to go to
You got to
admit that there's countless other
planets. In fact
there There
planets on which
uh
you know,
some guy is teaching Pabongka Rinpoche's
at this sentence,
there are countless planets
where some guy some guy with no hair
on top
is teaching Pabongka Rinpoche's
Lam Rim right now, this sentence. There
are countless planets
where somebody who looks just like Geshe
Michael
and by the way, who's not Geshe Michael,
but is teaching this sentence
right now,
logically, because it's infinite.
Uh so, the odds are infinite, okay? If
you roll the dice
a billion times, you'll get every
number.
So,
if you're able to break out past this
one world,
then
make up means stuff you want to
accomplish today.
This afternoon, we have a book
publishing meeting after the class,
right?
Something you want to accomplish this
afternoon or tartuki done, your pursuit
of total enlightenment,
they made to do, you can accomplish
these things without any hassle at all,
okay? Not much work.
Okay?
And then eventually, you can get to the
highest
goal of all, which what's that?
Uh
help every person in the universe
get rid of all of their trouble and
pain, and
uh help them get everything they want,
okay?
If you just have this
if you're able to break out from this
one world to all worlds, okay?
Uh
they would do but you chinjugle, he
quotes chinjug,
Good. If you guys didn't get that right,
you would have to pay me $100. That's
where all this thing is headed.
You think I'm being generous, but
I'm going to flip it someday.
Uh,
they need to make it with so long key.
They told they learn it to top our song.
The Buddha said
that you can easily help countless
beings if you just break out of this
world. Just break out of this one world
to the idea that you could help all all
beings in all worlds, okay?
All right.
Let's see.
Shannyak.
Uh, Sam dig you like in a good day so
glad [__] then they're not the mental me
pal the pal give me do but time to come
to me to do more.
He says, "Look, uh,
lots of people trying to practice
tantra. Lots of people say, 'I'm going
to practice diamond way. I'm going to do
Vajrayana or I'm going to do medicine
Buddha or I'm going to do Amitabha.'
You know, lots of people trying to
practice mantras
uh,
to succeed
in these higher prac- secret practices,
okay? Sam dig you like in a
If you enter those practices with just a
little bit of bodhicitta
imagination, you know, like I'm I'm
breaking out from this planet. I'm
helping everybody on all planets. If you
approach your mantras your daughter
niece
with this kind of feeling in your heart,
then
uh,
shape it in a
you will succeed. Sek me. Say sek me.
Sek me.
Sek me means no hassle.
Okay, sek means hassle.
It's a cute word. Uh, sek me ma. Easy,
okay? So, just get this motivation a
little bit.
Study Lam Rim study Bodhicitta. Then go
do your medicine Buddha mantras, your
Dharanis.
And super powerful. Okay? Then they will
work.
They will work for you. And they won't
work me pel don pelky.
If you just have normal thoughts, normal
worldly thoughts, and you're not
breaking out of this world to help
others. That's called here it's called
normal normal. He says, "If you're just
a normal normal pel pel pel don pel." By
the way, it's not the other pel which is
glorious, right?
If you're just pel pel
uh if you're just like
stuck in the everyday world mindum
your mantras won't work.
Okay? They won't work. Mindum means it
won't work. Okay? What's the famous
person whose name has dum
dum dum
dum dum Siddhartha. Okay? Siddhartha.
Okay? Whose name means the prince
Siddhartha who was the Buddha.
His name means you get things done.
Okay? And he says here
if you don't
think about breaking out of this world,
and you just sit there and do mantras
mindum means no asiddha. You you won't
reach your goals. The the mantras won't
help you. Okay?
You got to
have this gasoline
in the car called Bodhicitta. Then the
car of secret practice, medicine Buddha,
Vajrayogini
Amitabha, Tara, it will work for you.
Okay?
Yay! And we have a big machine I think
somewhere.
What was that machine?
Yeah, I was trying to find a big
machine, you know.
Like
this is what Tantra looks like to me. I
mean, Vajrayana, Diamond Way.
It's this huge, powerful machine.
And
it's got to have electricity, all right?
And it doesn't matter how powerful the
machine is
if it doesn't have electricity, it won't
run.
Okay, what's electricity?
Body tinana, yeah, good. Okay.
All right, we're going on to
class
six, which is where we're supposed to
start today, I think.
If I'm not mistaken. Okay, Geshe now is
a little behind. It's very unusual.
Class six.
Uh
dodan gyude byur bum sog la shepa
chambup. Now he's talking about
uh
Buddhist practices
that are supposed to get you things.
Okay, like little Buddhist practices,
like you're supposed to get money
or you're supposed to get over your
as- asthma or your allergies, you you
know.
Or your mother-in-law's supposed to
suddenly love you.
You know,
they they're specific little
Buddhist rituals that I haven't
spent time with you
teaching you.
Uh but there are little books called
overcoming
baldness or
you know,
uh wrinkles or
or these are little books There are
little books like that. Uh
we we haven't studied them.
But he says, "Look, uh
there's little practices The examples he
gives is chambep
which means making it rain
in a desert or something like that.
I think that would be useful for the
carbon offset project.
Uh and Tenzin Bump
uh
ser sum, that's ser
protecting from ser
hail, hailstones.
And these are called ten ser. Ten ser
means uh
Ten ser is kind of a put down, uh little
little miscellaneous Buddhist rituals,
okay? Little
miscellaneous rituals. Ten ser nam kyong
sheb shin men drupa
You know, people like you and me, we
read the
nyen chos means us guys, though we read
from sutras. You we read from tantras,
from secret teachings.
And bul bum, bul bum means uh
like chronicles.
Okay? We read these little
We read about these rituals like making
it rain
or stopping hail or, you know,
stopping the wind at Diamond Mountain.
Uh
ten ser nam kyong sheb shin men drupa,
but they never seem to work, you know?
Like we go we go get a book, we
translate it, it's how to make things
rain, we do the whole ritual, you know,
as the book says, and then nothing
happens, okay?
And he says, "Guess what?
Yeah, chan chos sem me pel men me pel
men me.
The problem is
you don't have bodhicitta when you did
those rituals. Don't think
those little ritual books are mistaken.
They're not. They're correct. They work.
But you don't have bodhicitta, so it's
not going to rain.
Okay?
You got to have
It's also the gasoline for the little
engines.
Okay.
And I think we have a picture there.
I don't know. I I see it like uh
a bunch of gears
and one of the gears is broken, okay?
And that's your
bodhicitta. The whole machine is fine.
The texts are fine. The ritual is fine.
You know, it should work. But there's
one gear that's broken, which is your
motivation. You don't have this
motivation beyond this small world,
okay?
All right. Tänna
wang shing gyi nyam tsa so
par che sel shing nyur du chir wa dön
So, if you want to do things like
removing people's cancer
or uh helping friends to get over
serious diseases, things like that, fix
their eyeballs,
stuff like that.
Sem bkyed kyis you got to have this
motivation when you do those rituals.
When you say those mantras,
when you do those tönlen,
if you don't have this motivation,
something's broken in the machine and it
won't work, okay?
Ngag kyi lä min grub pa de dag lä sol
tam me mang akhi men.
If the lä min grub means here it means
if the ritual doesn't work,
de dag lä sol tam me mang akhi men. It's
not a problem with the translation or
it's not a problem with the text, okay?
It's not that John Brady got the wrong
book in the Mongolian library, okay?
Don't blame John Brady.
Although he's generally responsible for
everything.
Uh
nyam pa tab bu cha mi rung. Nyam pa cha
means don't think like that. You know,
don't think John Brady got the wrong
book
uh for making it rain. He got the right
book.
But you didn't have bodhicitta when you
did the ritual, okay? Don't think that
Dr. Woo didn't get the right medicine
Buddha
ritual and and you it's not working for
you.
It's your motivation, okay? All right.
Mhm.
And then we have a picture of a lady
going for a
MRI in the hospital. Yeah.
I don't know. I I had one of these done.
It's It's frightening, right? I don't
know. They They put you in this tube
and I think it's Somebody told me it's
like 5,000 x-rays or something, which
doesn't sound healthy.
And uh
but uh
if you if you really want to cure a
cancer or something,
then those rituals can work. Medicine
Buddha mantras can work,
but you got to have the electricity. You
got to have the the motivation, okay?
Which has to be more than fixing one
person.
All right. Dema say hum hum phat phat.
Hum hum phat phat.
I don't know. I don't like phat cuz it
sounds like fat.
And uh then I always think I'm eating
too much. But anyway, phat is uh
what do you call threatening gesture for
uh
phat,
you know, uh in a Buddhist ritual. Aum
nak means Dharani or mantras.
Dze means uh you make some secret,
you know,
liquid or something
to help you with the ritual, okay?
Dze sokla tsemay guky.
That's not the secret ingredient. It's
It's the body chedda, okay? So, you
know, if you don't have hum hum phat
phat and uh you forgot your uh namcha,
right?
Don't worry. Just replace it with some
body chedda and you're fine.
Okay? If you don't know how to make all
these things, so don't worry about it.
The thing you have to make is from your
heart, right?
Cool.
Then said some good dude. Then he says
something very very powerful.
He says, "Do an act of truth. Do an act
of truth, okay?"
And this is very very famous
in ancient India.
And that classic example, who can tell
me?
Yeah, make the Ganges River flow
backwards, okay? So, the Ganges River,
if you've never been there,
if you're especially if you're on an
Indian bus,
uh
it can take an hour to cross it on the
bridge.
Uh it could take an hour to cross the
river in in the flat parts.
Uh
like if you're going to Bengal from
from West Bengal. If you're going to
Bangladesh from West Bengal,
then it can take an hour on the And it's
very fun cuz there's holes in the
bridge.
And the bus has to kind of go like this.
And uh
it takes about an hour to get across
that river. So, imagine
uh
a a
a spiritual practice
where you pray
that that river should flow backwards
towards the Himalayas, back to the
Himalayas up,
backwards to Mount Everest
because of your prayer, you know? Like
billions and
of gallons of water are going to turn
their direction and flow up the
Himalayas back to the snow mountain,
okay?
So,
this is called an act of truth. And
it means you you always say, "If it's
true
that I
you know, if it's true that I
made a coffee for Geshe La with my best
motivation this morning.
Uh then may the Ganges River flow
backwards
for half an hour or something. And then
it was a big disruption
in ancient India. All these guys doing
acts of truth. The their farms don't get
their irrigation.
The Ganges River's flowing backwards.
Okay. So, if it's true
that I did the tag or the translation
for the Lamrim
with a fairly good motivation.
Uh
then may the Ganges River flow backwards
today, you know. And that's called an
act of truth. Okay. Why does it come up
here?
Yeah. He says, "You You want to know the
best act of truth you could do?
It's It's Bodhicitta. If it's true
that this morning
during Geshe la's talk
I actually tried to break out of this
one world, this one planet,
and I I spent at least 20 seconds
trying to imagine helping people on
another world.
If that's true,
then I should get a good breakfast after
the class today.
Okay.
Something like that. Okay. Some glorious
act of truth.
All right.
So, uh
Okay. So, that's He says,
"If you want to go do that act of truth
thing, which is really fun,
then
Bodhicitta is the best one you can
choose. If If you can claim
that you tried to have Bodhicitta
for a few minutes this morning,
then you can make miracles happen.
You Based on that truth,
uh you can make miracles happen. Okay.
Now,
uh The Rinpoche says it's like the story
of the Bodhisattva
who's called crying all the time,
Sadaprarudita.
Okay? His name is Mr. Crying All the
Time. Okay? So, there's a very, very
famous uh
story.
And it's in the 8,000 verses on the
Perfection of Wisdom, Bodobolobol.
8,000 verses.
There are many
uh
Prajnaparamita
Sutras.
There's 100,000 verses, there's 15,000
verses, there's 25 or 20,000 verses,
there's
there's the Heart Sutra, which is two
pages.
And there's the 8,000 verses. The 8,000
verses
version
happens to be extremely sexy.
Okay? And I love science fiction. I love
to read science I read science fiction
every night. I can't eat unless I'm
reading science fiction.
And uh
I definitely can't go to bed without I
Oh, I'm supposed to do coffee
meditation, but usually it's mixed.
Uh
but uh
in that 8,000 verses
is much more beautiful than science
fiction. It's It's like the ultimate
science fiction. If you really like
science fiction, I I recommend the 8,000
verses. Okay?
It It's not uh
a Madhyamaka treatise. It sounds like
that, right? Perfection of Wisdom Sutra.
But when you really read them,
they are like detective novels.
They are like very exciting uh
story true stories of of cool things.
Okay? Anyway, there's a story
in the 8,000 verses
called the Bodhisattva who couldn't stop
crying.
You know?
And I always thought it was because he
was
compassionate.
You know, I always when I heard about
the stories
I always thought he was sitting in his
retreat cabin
at Diamond Mountain crying
all day out of compassion for
other people. And I and then I read the
story.
I read the story I I actually taught it
to a student
in 1983. How long was 17
Anyway, a lot of years ago.
We translated it.
So like 35 years ago, 40 years ago.
And
I don't know.
of over 40 years ago. And
it's extremely beautiful story, okay?
And
And so Pabongka Rinpoche says
this Bodhicitta
is also, you know, while we're on the
subject
uh that Bodhicitta gets you your wishes,
helps you make your wishes come true.
You should try and act the truth
with Bodhicitta like the Bodhisattva who
couldn't stop crying.
Like the Bodhisattva who couldn't stop
crying, you know? And then he goes on.
Then he goes on to another subject, you
know? And I don't know about you, but
I'm like
what's the story? You didn't tell the
story.
You know, he just said, "Oh, it's like
that story, you know?"
And then I feel frustrated, you know?
I'm like
dang, you know? We don't know what these
stories are. Don't think we know.
Don't assume Pabongka Rinpoche
that a bunch of foreigners in 2021
are going to know these stories cuz we
don't.
You know? So I have a proposal. I gave
it to Tim this morning.
Uh
I went and got the story.
It's extraordinary.
It's one of my favorite Buddhist books
of all time, and I have a lot of
favorites.
But this story is something ex- it's
extremely beautiful.
So, we decided this usual Lamrim
blackmail technique
that
if you're a volunteer
or if you agree to be a volunteer in the
future
for him
and for ACI
and Tatiana, all these guys, okay? If
you agree to be a volunteer
we'll have a special session this week
for you guys, and we'll cover that
story, okay? We'll go through that
story. So, some people like Pabongka
you're already in.
Okay,
everybody here is already in that group.
But I would love to tell the story.
And we don't actually we don't have time
in this class to do it. We'll get too
far behind.
So, it take about a half hour, something
like that.
And someday we should translate the
8,000 verses, but that would take it
would take about 50 years
to translate it, but it's it's extremely
beautiful.
Somebody should work on it.
So, that's a little
Dharma blackmail, okay?
I'm going to just skip the story
and
get in touch with Tim. We'll tell you
how you can
join that class. It's a bonus class,
okay?
We'll put a link in the chat right now.
Okay, cool. All right. So,
Pabongka Rinpoche only says
Changsem Takpu Mu, misspelled in the
carving, okay? Takpu they said Takpu Du.
You could you should refer
to the story
of the Bodhisattva who couldn't stop
crying. And why he couldn't stop crying
has nothing to do with compassion.
Okay? And that's a secret. And you got
to come to the half hour class to find
out.
Okay. Dentsiki Kulusu, he used an act of
truth
in the 8,000 verses. Okay?
Then he goes on. He just skips on. So,
I'm going to skip that story which I
have written out here.
The story is about It take about a half
hour, I think.
Class I taught. Then he goes on to
another
example
of an act of truth. So, Pabongka
Rinpoche goes on to another example
of an act of truth. And I think
uh
you know, we all I I'm hoping
that all of you will teach Lamrim.
You know, that that's the whole point
of teaching the whole thing for 10, 15
years.
Like my teacher did to me
is that I'm hoping you will teach it.
Okay? And then,
you know, you have to
understand the style of teaching Lamrim.
So, Lamrim, as you can tell, it's a lot
of stories, also.
And you never forget the stories. I
heard these stories first time uh
45 years ago. And I still remember the
stories. You don't forget the stories.
You forget
Madhyamaka, but you don't forget the
stories. Okay? So, uh
here's a story. And And when you teach
Lamrim,
you should use your own stories from
your own time and place. Okay? But
here's a story
from Pabongka Rinpoche's time and place.
In Tibet,
they're in the Himalayas.
There's a lot of snow.
That snow melts.
To To Tibet is laced with rivers
everywhere. You can't walk 2 miles
without having to cross a river, and
there's no bridges
at that time. Okay? So, the rivers were
dangerous.
And they were cold. Okay?
So,
you know, you had to find a a good place
to cross, all right? Lotsawa Sangchu.
So, there was a river that goes
near Lhasa, through Lhasa, and called
Sangchu.
And Sherab Gyaltsen Dolma Nupa. It used
to flood.
You know, there were flooding seasons
when it would over What do you call it?
The It would overflow the banks of the
river and destroy houses and things like
that.
Uh Dolma Nupa. Nobody could do anything
about it. One One time
the river was flooding.
Uh Jamyang Lodro. There was a lama
called Jamyang Lodro, Lodro. Okay?
And they said, "Can you help stop the
river?"
And he said, "Yeah, easy. Just act of
truth thing. It's just an act of truth
thing. It's the Come on, just do an act
of truth."
You know? So, they said, "Well, what's
your act of truth?" Uh Monlam Pelwa
Changchub Senge Yonten. So, yeah, I
guess you go like this. We got a
picture, right, pal?
Yeah, this guy's doing an act of truth.
I don't know why. He looks like a high
lama to me.
Uh
you know, he's like, "If it's true and
and this lama named Monlam Pel,
he said, "If it's true that I'm a
bodhisattva,
if it's true that I have bodhicitta,
then the river should
go back
and stop flooding. Okay? The river
should turn back to the banks of the
river, okay?
Changchub Senge Yonten. Denpa Di, by
this truth,
Chu Kyur, hey you, water,
Hey you river water.
Pani the dog, get your ass back to the
banks of the river. But it's very it's a
very colloquial.
He's talking to the water. Get get
yourself back to the
river bed. What are you doing here?
If I'm a Bodhisattva, you have to go
back, okay? And he they wrote it on a
stone
and they put the stone on the river
bank, okay?
Chur dam to kill when they might talk to
immediately Cho Palu, the the river
moved back to the river bed
and stopped flooding Lhasa city, okay?
Chung wang dente to do pa yin.
It was turned back by the power of
Bodhicitta. He swore
that he had Bodhicitta. He swore that he
had that name, right? That title.
Uh Bodhisattva, so the water didn't have
a choice. The water had to go back,
okay?
All right.
Deche donky to tamche kambe go pa ne
mata lezo tamashe yinche di dru.
And now he's wrapping up benefit number
seven, okay?
Now he's wrapping up benefit number
seven and he says, "Therefore,
to conclude,
we can say that uh
you can get
every every the whole range
of stuff you want to happen in your
life,
you can make it happen with Bodhicitta.
Starting with,
you know, I don't know. May I get a good
breakfast this morning?
Up to
may all beings in the universe be happy.
Starting from
breakfast at Diamond Mountain
up to
all the beings in the universe being
happy,
Bodhicitta is the key to get everything
you want.
to happen, okay? From this up to that.
We have 3 minutes. We have finished a
major section. What should we do?
Use the 3 minutes
to go on.
We will do Q&A. We do have a Q&A. Okay.
Let's just talk about benefit number
eight, okay?
By the way, while we're on benefit eight
out of 10 benefits and we're not like a
quarter finished with the
classes.
You can guess benefit 10 is big
and it's going to take a long time,
okay? Takes It probably takes as much
time as all the other ones.
Uh number eight uh
Obstacles can't touch you, okay? That
would be nice, right?
Like all of us are trying to
do Dharma projects. We're trying to
fundraise. We're trying to save ancient
books.
We're trying to help
hungry people. The Vietnam group, 6,000.
How many were there? 16,000 students in
the Vietnam group.
And they are building uh houses for poor
people.
Uh and they've built uh
uh if I'm not mistaken, it's 400 houses,
something like that. Uh for poor people.
Uh
and uh
you know,
you get obstacles when you're trying to
do big projects,
you get obstacles. And if you
are trying to do something good to help
other people
and you keep running into obstacles,
then the next section is for you.
Okay? You can stop all the obstacles to
your
cool projects
uh
by by doing a little Bodhicitta
meditation every day. So, we're going to
cover that next.
That's all I have today. Tim, you have
anything for
See you we'll take a 10-minute break
and you know, do the necessary as my
teacher used to say
and we'll see you in about 10 minutes.
Okay, thank you.